<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conference on Nicola Rennie</title>
    <link>https://nrennie.github.io/categories/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conference on Nicola Rennie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 09:30:59 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nrennie.github.io/categories/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>We&#39;re not getting any younger! Or should that be older?</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2021-september-rss-international-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 09:30:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2021-september-rss-international-conference/</guid>
      <description>At the same time as pension ages in the UK continue to rise, both academics and journalists claim that life expectancy is stalling. To investigate these claims, we look at changes in UK life expectancy growth from 1960 to present day. Using data from World Bank Open Data, we use a rolling window linear model to estimate how life expectancy has changed decade-by-decade. We find that though there has been a steep decline in life expectancy growth in the last ten years, the growth is still positive and life expectancy continues to increase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlying demand in multi-leg bookings for transportation networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2021-july-euro2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 10:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2021-july-euro2021/</guid>
      <description>Network effects complicate transport demand forecasting in general and outlier detection in particular. For example, a sudden increase in demand for a specific destination will not only affect the legs arriving at that destination, but also connected legs nearby in the network. Network effects are particularly strong when service providers, such as railway or coach companies, offer many multi-leg itineraries. In such situations, automated alerts can help analysts to adjust demand forecasts and enable reliable planning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlier demand in revenue management networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2021-april-ima-or-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 13:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2021-april-ima-or-conference/</guid>
      <description>Transport service providers, such as airlines or railways, often use revenue management systems to control ticket prices and availability. Such systems rely on accurately forecasting expected demand to prepare optimal capacity allocations. Extraordinary events generate outlier demand, and cause inaccurate forecasts resulting in non-optimal allocations. Most revenue management systems allow room for analysts to compare the accumulated bookings against the forecasts and to intervene, if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The identification of inaccurate demand estimates </title>
      <link>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2019-june-euro2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 08:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.github.io/talk/2019-june-euro2019/</guid>
      <description>Most quantity-based airline revenue management systems rely on forecasting expected demand to prepare revenue-optimal capacity allocations. Inaccurate demand forecasts result in non-optimal allocations and hence, hurt revenue. Most airline revenue management systems also allow room for analysts to compare the accumulated bookings against the forecasts and to intervene, if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate. Systematically detecting outliers, where demand differs from expectations due to systematic market shifts, e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
