<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Workshop on Nicola Rennie</title>
    <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/categories/workshop/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Workshop on Nicola Rennie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nrennie.rbind.io/categories/workshop/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlier demand in railway networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-february-airoyoung/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-february-airoyoung/</guid>
      <description>Transport service providers, such as airlines and railways, often use revenue manage-ment to control offers and demand in mobility networks. Such systems rely on accu-rate demand forecasts as input for the underlying optimisation models. When changes in the market place cause demand to deviate from the expected values, revenue man-agement controls no longer fit for the resulting outliers. Analysts can intervene if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate. However, existing research on judgemen-tal forecasting highlights fallibility and bias when human decision makers are not sys-tematically supported in such tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying and responding to outlier demand in revenue management</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2020-april-stori-pop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 12:15:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2020-april-stori-pop/</guid>
      <description>Revenue management strongly relies on accurate forecasts. Thus, when extraordinary events cause outlier demand, revenue management systems need to recognise this and adapt both forecast and controls. State-of-the-art systems rely on analyst expertise to identify outlier demand both online (within the booking horizon) and offline (in hindsight). In light of the partial nature of revenue management data and censoring effects from inventory controls, so far, there exists little research on automating the detection of outlier demand.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
