<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Workshop on Nicola Rennie</title>
    <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/categories/workshop/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Workshop on Nicola Rennie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nrennie.rbind.io/categories/workshop/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlier demand in railway networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-february-airoyoung/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-february-airoyoung/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transport service providers, such as airlines and railways, often use revenue manage-ment to control offers and demand in mobility networks. Such systems rely on accu-rate demand forecasts as input for the underlying optimisation models. When changes in the market place cause demand to deviate from the expected values, revenue man-agement controls no longer fit for the resulting outliers. Analysts can intervene if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate. However, existing research on judgemen-tal forecasting highlights fallibility and bias when human decision makers are not sys-tematically supported in such tasks. This motivates the need for automated alerts to highlight outliers and thereby support analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network effects complicate the problem of detecting outlier demand in practice. Pas-sengers often book travel itineraries that stretch across multiple legs of a network. Thereby, they requests products that require multiple resources &amp;ndash; seats on several legs. In the rail and long-distance coach industries, the large number of possible itiner-aries makes it likely for outlier demand to affect multiple legs. At the same time, outli-er demand from a single itinerary may be difficult to recognise as it mixes with regular demand on individual legs. To support outlier detection in transport networks, we pre-sent a method to aggregates outlier detection across highly correlated legs. We propose to use the results of this analysis to construct a ranked alert list that can support ana-lyst decision making. We show that by aggregating we are able to improve detection performance compared to considering each leg in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Revenue management, Networks, Outlier detection&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying and responding to outlier demand in revenue management</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2020-april-stori-pop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 12:15:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2020-april-stori-pop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revenue management strongly relies on accurate forecasts. Thus, when extraordinary events cause outlier demand, revenue management systems need to recognise this and adapt both forecast and controls. State-of-the-art systems rely on analyst expertise to identify outlier demand both online (within the booking horizon) and offline (in hindsight). In light of the partial nature of revenue management data and censoring effects from inventory controls, so far, there exists little research on automating the detection of outlier demand. To remedy this, we propose a novel approach, which detects outliers using functional data analysis in combination with extrapolation via time-series forecasting. We evaluate the approach in a simulation framework, which generates outliers by manipulating the demand model. By evaluating the full feedback-driven system of forecast and optimisation, we generate insight on the asymmetric effects of positive and negative demand outliers in light of revenue management heuristics that do or do not account for customer choice. Furthermore, we quantify the value of both online and offline outlier detection. We show that identifying instances of outlier demand using our methodology, and adjusting the forecast in a timely fashion, substantially increases revenue compared to what is earned when ignoring outliers. We also highlight some difficulties that may be encountered when deploying such alerting systems in a real revenue management system, and propose solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Revenue management; Simulation; Forecasting, Outlier detection; Functional data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>