<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks on Nicola Rennie</title>
    <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talks on Nicola Rennie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 10:30:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Women in Stats and Data Science at Lancaster University</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2022-march-international-womens-day-lu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 10:30:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2022-march-international-womens-day-lu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 8, 2022, Lancaster University hosted an online panel discussion on the career path of Women in Stats to celebrate International Womens&#39; Day. The speakers were Anastasia Ushakova, Carolina Euan, Emma Eastoe, Kathryn Turnbull and Nicola Rennie. My answers to the five main questions are below:&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-do-you-do-on-a-typical-day-at-work&#34;&gt;What do you do on a typical day at work?
  &lt;a href=&#34;#what-do-you-do-on-a-typical-day-at-work&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it&amp;rsquo;s easier to answer this in terms of a typical week rather than typical day since I tend to have quite a varied schedule. In my job, I do a combination of data science consultancy and running training courses - mostly on programming in R. So a typical week for me, is maybe two half days of teaching (online at the moment). I would also spend sometime preparing for teaching, and developing or updating course material. In terms of consultancy, I spend two or three days a week on client work. For me, that could be a wide range of things - it could be statistical advice i.e., helping clients decide which methods to use; it could be building dashboards; it could be reviewing code that a client has written. Then I also usually spend another day of my week doing internal consultancy, so projects that Jumping Rivers are working on internally. That might be building a website for a conference, running workshops at conferences, or automating some of our admin processes. That&amp;rsquo;s a typical week, but no two days are exactly the same and I can mostly pick-and-choose what I do on each day of the week.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h4 id=&#34;when-and-why-did-you-decide-to-work-in-statisticsdata-science&#34;&gt;When and why did you decide to work in statistics/data science?
  &lt;a href=&#34;#when-and-why-did-you-decide-to-work-in-statisticsdata-science&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my undergrad (in maths), I didn&amp;rsquo;t really do many stats courses until my final year. And I liked it. It seemed more applied than most of the applied maths I&amp;rsquo;d spent the first few years doing. So I decided to go and do a stats PhD, which I did at STOR-i. I knew I wanted apply whatever I was learning so I was probably leaning more towards working in industry even before I started my PhD. During my PhD, I had an industrial partner - I collaborated with Deutsche Bahn, and I enjoyed that part of my PhD a lot more than the research side of things. I found myself wanting to spend time developing dashboards or playing with data more than I wanted to write papers (or my thesis). So I think at that point, I thought: okay, let&amp;rsquo;s find a job where I can spend my time doing the type of work I enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-aspects-of-the-job-are-most-appealing-least-appealing&#34;&gt;What aspects of the job are most appealing? Least appealing?
  &lt;a href=&#34;#what-aspects-of-the-job-are-most-appealing-least-appealing&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most appealing? I think there are two things I really like about my job. One is the variety of projects I get to work on. Both in terms of the application, and in terms of the actual technical work I&amp;rsquo;m doing. The other thing I really enjoy is delivering work to clients, there&amp;rsquo;s quite a lot of job satisfaction in that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Least appealing? I&amp;rsquo;m actually very lucky in that I&amp;rsquo;m now in a job that I really like pretty much everything about it. I guess one thing would be, sometimes we have to compromise on how fancy soe of our methodology is. You know, we might have an idea for a very complex method that could work for a very specific problem, but (i) simple methods are easier to explain to clients; (ii) they&amp;rsquo;re generally faster to build and run.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-skills-are-essential-for-success-in-this-career-hard-and-soft-skills&#34;&gt;What skills are essential for success in this career? (Hard and soft skills)
  &lt;a href=&#34;#what-skills-are-essential-for-success-in-this-career-hard-and-soft-skills&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of hard (technical) skills, programming skills are the obvious one. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to be proficient in every programming language, but at the very least having an awareness of the programming languages that are commonly used (e.g., R, Python), and having done some work in one of them. I would also recommend getting used to working with version control early. It&amp;rsquo;s probably easier to practice using something like git when you&amp;rsquo;re the only person working on a project. If you&amp;rsquo;re confident using it on your own, then it&amp;rsquo;ll make it easier to scale up and join an existing project which already has hundreds of scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of soft skills, I think being able to talk to people about maths without using maths-y words is really important. A lot of the time, clients will come to us for advice and they don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily know what the problem is. They also don&amp;rsquo;t usually have a statistics background. So being able to sit down and talk to them about what they want the end result to be, and what&amp;rsquo;s most important to them, is usually the first step in defining the data science problem that you&amp;rsquo;re actually going to be working on. It&amp;rsquo;s unlikely that a client comes to you with a perfectly formed, textbook data science problem.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;h4 id=&#34;if-i-decided-to-pursue-this-career-path-what-advice-would-you-give-me&#34;&gt;If I decided to pursue this career path, what advice would you give me?
  &lt;a href=&#34;#if-i-decided-to-pursue-this-career-path-what-advice-would-you-give-me&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to work for a company where you&amp;rsquo;re invested in the bigger picture of what they do. Everybody has days where something&amp;rsquo;s not working, and you just want to throw your laptop out the window. That&amp;rsquo;s perfectly normal. When you&amp;rsquo;re studying, you&amp;rsquo;re invested in getting a degree so you have a good reason to not throw your laptop out the window. But when you&amp;rsquo;re working for a company, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to be quite as personally invested in your work, but those sort of difficult days are easier if you like the company you work for, and you like the work that they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also say, don&amp;rsquo;t be put off for applying for a job because you don&amp;rsquo;t tick every box on the criteria. Most good employers are willing to spend time developing employees, because data science as a field is developing constantly. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to learn new things all the time anyway. And someone that is willing to learn whatever they need to is more valuable to an employer in the longer term. So just go for opportunities when they&amp;rsquo;re there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Featured image: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@hannahbusing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hannah Busing&lt;/a&gt; on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/Zyx1bK9mqmA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We&#39;re not getting any younger! Or should that be older?</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-september-rss-international-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 09:30:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-september-rss-international-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the same time as pension ages in the UK continue to rise, both academics and journalists claim that life expectancy is stalling. To investigate these claims, we look at changes in UK life expectancy growth from 1960 to present day. Using data from World Bank Open Data, we use a rolling window linear model to estimate how life expectancy has changed decade-by-decade. We find that though there has been a steep decline in life expectancy growth in the last ten years, the growth is still positive and life expectancy continues to increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, just as life expectancies are not equal for men and women, neither are the changes in life expectancy growth. Whilst life expectancy has stalled for women in the UK, men continue to get older - albeit more slowly than they used to. The gap between the life expectancies for men and women is closing and we estimate that, given current trends continue, both men and women will have an equal life expectancy of 85.2 years by 2100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We extend our analyses beyond the UK, and examine how trends in life expectancy in the last decade differ between the most and least developed countries in the world. Countries where life expectancy has stalled are identified, and we discuss the commonalities found in such countries in terms of level of development and current life expectancy age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It&amp;#39;s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rss2021conf?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#rss2021conf&lt;/a&gt; this week! I&amp;#39;m looking forward to catching up with the online sessions later. I&amp;#39;ll be talking about my work on life expectancy trends in the RSS Prize winners: Statistical excellence award for early career writing session on Wednesday. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/QTarThkRy7&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/QTarThkRy7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nicola Rennie (@nrennie35) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nrennie35/status/1434867512710152198?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 6, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;twitter-share-button&#34;
href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet&#34;
data-size=&#34;large&#34;&gt;
Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlying demand in multi-leg bookings for transportation networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-july-euro2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 10:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-july-euro2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Network effects complicate transport demand forecasting in general and outlier detection in particular. For example, a sudden increase in demand for a specific destination will not only affect the legs arriving at that destination, but also connected legs nearby in the network. Network effects are particularly strong when service providers, such as railway or coach companies, offer many multi-leg itineraries. In such situations, automated alerts can help analysts to adjust demand forecasts and enable reliable planning. 
In this presentation, we outline a novel two-step method for automatically detecting outlying demand from transportation network bookings. The first step clusters network legs according to the observed booking patterns. The second step identifies outliers within each cluster to create a ranked alert list of affected legs. We illustrate the method using empirical data obtained from Deutsche Bahn. In addition, we present a detailed simulation study that quantifies the improvement from the clustering step and implications of ranking to measure the criticality of the outliers. Our results show that the proposed approach outperforms independently analysing each leg, especially in highly connected networks where most passengers book multi-leg itineraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Analytics; Forecasting; Outlier detection; Network analysis; Simulation; Demand management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlier demand in revenue management networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-april-ima-or-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 13:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-april-ima-or-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transport service providers, such as airlines or railways, often use revenue management systems to control ticket prices and availability. Such systems rely on accurately forecasting expected demand to prepare optimal capacity allocations. Extraordinary events generate outlier demand, and cause inaccurate forecasts resulting in non-optimal allocations. Most revenue management systems allow room for analysts to compare the accumulated bookings against the forecasts and to intervene, if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate. However, research on judgemental forecasting has clearly demonstrated the existence of fallibility and bias in such practices. This motivates the need for automated alerts to highlight outlier demand, and thereby support analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of detecting outlier demand is further complicated by the consideration of network effects. Passengers often book tickets that require multiple resources across a network. For example, a train ticket may be booked for a journey that passes through multiple stations. In the railway industry, there are a large number of possible itineraries and most customers book journeys for multiple legs. In this case, outlier demand is unlikely to affect only a single leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a method for aggregating outlier detection across multiple legs in a railway network, which leverages functional analysis and extreme value theory. In a set of controlled simulation scenarios, we let demand systematically deviate from the general level, and evaluate the method’s ability to detect outlier demand.. We show that by aggregating; we are able to both increase detection rates, and reduce false positive rates, in comparison to considering each leg in isolation. We demonstrate the practical implications of detecting outliers across networks by applying the procedure to empirical booking data obtained from Deutsche Bahn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Revenue management; Simulation; Decision support; Outlier detection; Functional analysis; Network analysis&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting outlier demand in railway networks</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-february-airoyoung/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2021-february-airoyoung/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transport service providers, such as airlines and railways, often use revenue manage-ment to control offers and demand in mobility networks. Such systems rely on accu-rate demand forecasts as input for the underlying optimisation models. When changes in the market place cause demand to deviate from the expected values, revenue man-agement controls no longer fit for the resulting outliers. Analysts can intervene if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate. However, existing research on judgemen-tal forecasting highlights fallibility and bias when human decision makers are not sys-tematically supported in such tasks. This motivates the need for automated alerts to highlight outliers and thereby support analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network effects complicate the problem of detecting outlier demand in practice. Pas-sengers often book travel itineraries that stretch across multiple legs of a network. Thereby, they requests products that require multiple resources &amp;ndash; seats on several legs. In the rail and long-distance coach industries, the large number of possible itiner-aries makes it likely for outlier demand to affect multiple legs. At the same time, outli-er demand from a single itinerary may be difficult to recognise as it mixes with regular demand on individual legs. To support outlier detection in transport networks, we pre-sent a method to aggregates outlier detection across highly correlated legs. We propose to use the results of this analysis to construct a ranked alert list that can support ana-lyst decision making. We show that by aggregating we are able to improve detection performance compared to considering each leg in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Revenue management, Networks, Outlier detection&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying and responding to outlier demand in revenue management</title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2020-april-stori-pop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 12:15:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2020-april-stori-pop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Revenue management strongly relies on accurate forecasts. Thus, when extraordinary events cause outlier demand, revenue management systems need to recognise this and adapt both forecast and controls. State-of-the-art systems rely on analyst expertise to identify outlier demand both online (within the booking horizon) and offline (in hindsight). In light of the partial nature of revenue management data and censoring effects from inventory controls, so far, there exists little research on automating the detection of outlier demand. To remedy this, we propose a novel approach, which detects outliers using functional data analysis in combination with extrapolation via time-series forecasting. We evaluate the approach in a simulation framework, which generates outliers by manipulating the demand model. By evaluating the full feedback-driven system of forecast and optimisation, we generate insight on the asymmetric effects of positive and negative demand outliers in light of revenue management heuristics that do or do not account for customer choice. Furthermore, we quantify the value of both online and offline outlier detection. We show that identifying instances of outlier demand using our methodology, and adjusting the forecast in a timely fashion, substantially increases revenue compared to what is earned when ignoring outliers. We also highlight some difficulties that may be encountered when deploying such alerting systems in a real revenue management system, and propose solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: Revenue management; Simulation; Forecasting, Outlier detection; Functional data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The identification of inaccurate demand estimates </title>
      <link>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2019-june-euro2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 08:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nrennie.rbind.io/talks/2019-june-euro2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most quantity-based airline revenue management systems rely on forecasting expected demand to prepare revenue-optimal capacity allocations. Inaccurate demand forecasts result in non-optimal allocations and hence, hurt revenue. Most airline revenue management systems also allow room for analysts to compare the accumulated bookings against the forecasts and to intervene, if they deem the demand forecast to be inaccurate. Systematically detecting outliers, where demand differs from expectations due to systematic market shifts, e.g., induced by special events, is an open challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a set of controlled simulation scenarios, we let demand systematically deviate from the general level. After transforming demand into bookings via a minimal revenue management simulation, we apply a variety of outlier detection techniques to determine whether the number of bookings can be classified as either normal or abnormal. The comparison includes a Euclidean distance-based approach, K-means clustering, and tolerance intervals and evaluates the ability to detect genuine outlying demand and false positive rates. We evaluate and discuss effects of unexpected demand on revenue, confirming previous findings that inaccurate demand estimates can result in a loss of potential revenue. We show that identifying instances of outlier demand and adjusting the forecast in a timely fashion has the potential to increase revenue. Hence, we show that the use of outlier detection techniques as an assistant to revenue management analysts can help to minimise such losses, and we provide best-case-scenario analysis of potential revenue gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: revenue management; simulation; demand estimation; tolerance intervals; decision support&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>